<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Yizhe Tang]]></title>
  <link href="http://typd.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://typd.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-08T00:56:57+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://typd.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Yizhe Tang]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[othertang@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Security industry intro]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2015/10/28/security-industry-intro/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-28T23:15:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2015/10/28/security-industry-intro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://yixi.tv/lecture/314">A talk</a> from the founder of wooyun.</p>

<p>As he said, the motivation was the illness of the web security industry.</p>

<ul>
<li>Web companies value themselves by how much user info they hold</li>
<li>But they care more about their business rather than the responsibility/safety</li>
<li>Only big companies would have security stuff. Even though they are far from doing a good job.</li>
<li>Users should care the security, but their interests are disturbed away, by the companies. Users don&rsquo;t/can&rsquo;t really know about the scenes behind.</li>
<li>The companies ignore security issues even more as users don&rsquo;t care.</li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s a dead lock. Also that&rsquo;s a bad ecosystem of the hackers. They would take the advantage of the leaks rather than report back to the source, which don&rsquo;t care too much.</p>

<p>To jump out there, someone should do &ldquo;the right thing&rdquo; remarkably. That is, attract hackers to report leaks to the source through a public influential channel. Make companies treat them seriously, and open to public after fixing.</p>

<p>Easier said than done. Technicals, influence, and patience are needed.</p>

<p>More and more data are getting on cloud. In this age, so many things are being unified. One may have huge impact to all, either it&rsquo;s something good, or bad, or even a disaster. Unifing means risks, fragilities. But people are still pursuing better experience, modern life. This is a social evolution nobody can reverse. Only science fictions know the end.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revelution OS]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2015/10/20/revelution-os/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-20T23:56:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2015/10/20/revelution-os</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.bilibili.com/video/av909925/">Revolution OS</a> is a movie about the birth of GNU, Linux, open source definition and so on.</p>

<p>Free software movement and Open Source</p>

<ul>
<li>Free software movement aims to the attitude of life. Open source is more about publishing the source code of software.

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;GNU is an operating system that is free software—that is, it respects users&#8217; freedom. The development of GNU made it possible to use a computer without software that would trample your freedom.&rdquo; <a href="http://www.gnu.org/">http://www.gnu.org/</a></li>
<li>Open source definition <a href="http://opensource.org/osd/">http://opensource.org/osd/</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>GNU and Linux</p>

<ul>
<li>GNU tended to release people from using private software. It completed the software first, but stucked on writing the kernel. Then linux came out to be a perfect kernel fit. People combined those two and called GNU/Linux. Later on, other distributions of linux like SuSE/Linux, Red Hat linux came out.</li>
<li>Linus said himself is an &ldquo;engineer&rdquo;, while Richard Stallman is a &ldquo;philosopher&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How app works on heroku]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/06/02/how-app-works-on-heroku/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T22:32:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/06/02/how-app-works-on-heroku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Heroku is a lead service in the Paas field. The <a href="http://12factor.net/">12 factor app</a> is a good summarize of their experiences on how to build a service. Util I&rsquo;ve read <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/how-heroku-works">this &ldquo;how heroku works&rdquo; spec</a>, and deployed a service recently, now I know more or less how they achieve that.</p>

<blockquote><h1>Deploy</h1>

<ul>
<li>Applications consist of your source code, a description of any dependencies, and a Procfile.</li>
<li>Procfiles list process types &ndash; named commands that you may want executed.</li>
<li>Deploying applications involves sending the application to Heroku using git.</li>
<li>Buildpacks lie behind the slug compilation process. Buildpacks take your application, its dependencies, and the language runtime, and produce slugs.</li>
<li>A slug is a bundle of your source, fetched dependencies, the language runtime, and compiled/generated output of the build system &ndash; ready for execution.</li>
<li>Config vars contain customizable configuration data that can be changed independently of your source code. The configuration is exposed to a running application via environment variables.</li>
<li>Add-ons are third party, specialized, value-added cloud services that can be easily attached to an application, extending its functionality.</li>
<li>A release is a combination of a slug (your application), config vars and add-ons. Heroku maintains an append-only ledger of releases you make.</li>
</ul>


<h1>Runtime</h1>

<ul>
<li>Dynos are isolated, virtualized unix containers, that provide the environment required to run an application.</li>
<li>Your application’s dyno formation is the total number of currently-executing dynos, divided between the various process types you have scaled.</li>
<li>The dyno manager is responsible for managing dynos across all applications running on Heroku.</li>
<li>Applications with only a single web dyno sleep after one hour of inactivity by the dyno manager. Scaling to multiple web dynos will avoid this.</li>
<li>One-off Dynos are temporary dynos that run with their input/output attached to your local terminal. They’re loaded with your latest release.</li>
<li>Each dyno gets its own ephemeral filesystem &ndash; with a fresh copy of the most recent release. It can be used as temporary scratchpad, but changes to the filesystem are not reflected to other dynos.</li>
<li>Logplex automatically collates log entries from all the running dynos of your app, as well as other components such as the routers, providing a single source of activity.</li>
<li>Scaling an application involves varying the number of dynos of each process type.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h1>About heroku</h1>

<ul>
<li>As a Paas, I think it&rsquo;s more friendly than Google App Engine. And the specs are good.</li>
<li>No judgement on the stability, real service cost yet.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn from Smartisan T1 Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/05/29/learn-from-smartisan-t1-conference/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-29T11:02:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/05/29/learn-from-smartisan-t1-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>事隔几天，看完了<a href="http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XNzE0Nzc0OTQ0.html">老罗的Smartisan T1发布会</a>。时长两个半小时只一个人演讲，能吸引我在屏幕前不换台，当然是有其牛逼之处的。</p>

<h1>对行业本身的信息</h1>

<ul>
<li>电子消费品的全行业产业链可谓已经十分成熟。芯片、机型制造、相机、电池、系统、客服、物流，哪怕是大家各自标榜的“人性化”设计，其实都有足够成熟、专业的分解提供商，真正“自家”的，大概主要是拍板产品理念，对各提供商产品的使用、组装，和必要的软件开发。当然这也不简单，不过还是有些攒机之感。</li>
<li>苹果太成功，让大家心悦诚服的追赶。苹果固然有产业链中积累的优势，但后起者都信心满满觉得可以超越。雷军说苹果卖服务，老罗说卖软件，但都不认为核心是硬件本身，这点起码靠谱。</li>
</ul>


<h1>演讲和营销策略</h1>

<ul>
<li>说老罗会演讲，恐怕大多数人不会反对，以前&#8221;老罗英语学校&#8221;的第一年演讲也不错</li>
<li>作为后起的&#8221;小厂商&#8221;，营销策略尤为重要，这里做的也很聪明

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;我很懂每一个环节，芯片、声音、相机、设计、软件等等&#8221;（当然你说还不够）</li>
<li>&ldquo;我用了最牛逼的芯片，声音调试，相机调试，设计，你可以不相信我，但谁谁谁你认识吧，不否认吧，软件我做的，我演示给你看；我就是搅局者，别以为别家每个环节都是自己做的，他们也不过是组装商，还没有好的选择品味。&rdquo;</li>
<li>额外的心理营销，找到独特的痛点：捐助openSSL，门票抵现，防摔保险，背夹电池</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h1>一些感受</h1>

<ul>
<li>手机固然是兵家必争之地，如此激烈的竞争中还能创新，确实值得佩服。即便是用了那么多外包的服务，不可否认这个团队认真的思考了方方面面，组装也是品味要求</li>
<li>另一方面，产业链确实更成熟了，设计的作用日渐突出，这也是很多快速发展事务中更迭尤其快的部分。设计的创新可以带动一个产业</li>
<li>也不难理解越来越多的设计资源集中在了电子产品上，更多资金、人力投入让这个产业的设计水准可以与汽车、家居等设计集中领领域比较。<a href="http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XNTIwMjg0MTky.html">工业设计的发展过程本身也很有意思</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Catch up the change]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/05/20/catch-up-the-change/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-20T13:38:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/05/20/catch-up-the-change</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A senior co-worker gave a talk about his work and philosophy, which is interesting.</p>

<p>His team called &ldquo;DevOps&rdquo; has build the internal development infrastructure, similar to AWS (manage machines) and heroku (service container), and other common tools. Those are useful and critical, but &ldquo;not the goal of the team&rdquo;. The motivation was not to build the Paas (internal heroku) itself, but to unify the developers way of handling the details around a service, like deployment, dependencies, logging, etc. (heroku has a high level <a href="http://12factor.net/">spec to explain the idea</a>). We don&rsquo;t want to sacrifice either speed or quality. To achieve that, building the service container platform is a smart choice, for coaching devs, and improving quality. So the idea behind, is really about improving the tech culture.</p>

<p>Jump out of there, this &ldquo;implicit&rdquo; way of doing things is rather &ldquo;interesting&rdquo;. The modern software development is creative and collaborative, especially for quality ones. It has become a social practise in many ways. Not only the market, requirements, dev language, tools, knowledge are changing, people also come and go. It&rsquo;s not always pratical to &ldquo;force&rdquo; all acting in a certain way. But you can &ldquo;lead&rdquo; the majority to catch up the change.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What makes a good engineering culture?]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/04/22/what-makes-a-good-engineering-culture/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-22T13:58:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/04/22/what-makes-a-good-engineering-culture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had many posts talk about engineering culture. Here&rsquo;s <a href="http://goo.gl/2VlzmQ">a good one</a> from others summaries the characters of a good culture.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Optimize for iteration speed

<ul>
<li>Team-wise, fast iteration speed means having a set of strong leaders to help coordinate and drive team efforts</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Push relentlessly toward automation

<ul>
<li>deploying, testing, etc</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Build the right software abstractions</li>
<li>Develop a focus on high code quality with code reviews</li>
<li>Maintain a respectful work environment</li>
<li>Build shared ownership of code</li>
<li>Allot 20% time</li>
<li>Build a culture of learning and continuous improvement</li>
<li>Hire the best</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>This can be a check list for evaluating a company.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About onboarding process]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/04/22/about-onboarding-process/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-22T13:45:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/04/22/about-onboarding-process</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When joining a new place, many devs may have similar situation as <a href="http://goo.gl/8n7hZv">this artical</a> described:</p>

<blockquote><p>I found myself wading through a codebase laced with technical debt and augmented with little documentation and no unit tests, written in a Java-like language called ActionScript that I wasn’t familiar with. I had two weeks to build and launch a feature already promised to video publishers, a feature that would allow them to schedule when their online videos would go on the air.</p></blockquote>

<p>And later some better onboarding experiences made him think what a good process should be.</p>

<p><strong>First, does it worth to invest time to onboarding process?</strong></p>

<blockquote><p> The onboarding process is an opportunity to direct the learning and the activity of a new hire toward what the team believes matters most.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Quora&rsquo;s goals when designing the process</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Ramp up a new employee as quickly as possible</li>
<li>Impart the startup’s culture and values</li>
<li>Expose the new employee to the breadth of fundamentals needed to succeed

<ul>
<li>Those engineers who learned the fundamental tools and abstractions well will do better</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Socially integrate the new employee onto the team</li>
</ul>


<p>There&rsquo;re more details to describe how they archive these goals.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is design about?]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/what-is-design-about/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-14T15:47:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/04/14/what-is-design-about</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a <a href="http://goo.gl/bcjRYc">good talk</a> tells &ldquo;what is design about&rdquo;.</p>

<ul>
<li>Focus, deliver quality</li>
<li>Compromise</li>
<li>Think about the context</li>
<li>Worry about the right thing: users&#8217; problem, not yours

<ul>
<li>Design thinking must trickle down

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Great design is a symptom of a design-led org structure &amp; engineering process&rdquo;</li>
<li>Design is not democratic</li>
<li>Design is not beautiful pictures either: can&rsquo;t separate engineering and design</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Design is about: understanding humans, and make things for humans

<ul>
<li>psychology</li>
<li>neuroscience</li>
<li>linguistics</li>
<li>sociology</li>
<li>philosophy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Empathy, details matter</li>
</ul>


<p>The presenter gave a good example of washing machine at the end. Remind me of designing an interface in programming.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Michael Jordan's 3rd Champion]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/03/31/michael-jordans-3rd-champion/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T23:33:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/03/31/michael-jordans-3rd-champion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>仔细读完了<a href="http://my.hupu.com/zhangjiawei/blog/6424835.html">这篇</a>文章，介绍公牛第三冠的幕前幕后。92-93还不是我看球的年纪，但以现在的理解，读起来感同身受。</p>

<p>竞技体育从来不止于体育本身，运动提供平台，加上太多技术的、战术的、心理的、团队的、社会的因素。不同层次的球员，不同层次的理解，在面对不同的问题。这到底是团队运动，神如乔丹也不能以一敌五，但神如乔丹可以理解比赛，推动队友。</p>

<p>像之前一篇里老师讲的，体育比赛和交响乐相似，因为足够复杂，才足够吸引人。简单的东西容易腻，复杂的东西看也看不完。</p>

<p>北京金隅昨天夺冠，37的老马还能找到和带领球队，真是幸事。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['Solving hard things early' from Facebook VP]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/03/23/solving-hard-things-early-from-facebook-vp/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T23:31:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/03/23/solving-hard-things-early-from-facebook-vp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Information technology is a fast industry now. Companies come and go. People keep thinking about new strategy of management in such rapid growing. <a href="http://ondrejka.net/">Facebook engineering VP</a> gives an <a href="http://firstround.com/article/Facebook-VP-of-Engineering-on-Solving-Hard-Things-Early">experience sharing</a> talk, which has many good points. Below are some quotes with my comments.</p>

<h1>Common mistakes</h1>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Every early stage company thinks it has reinvented management. In fact they have not!</li>
<li>Management is not about who is who’s boss. Management is the opportunity to explicitly choose tradeoffs. No silver bullet for all!</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s a very good point that you should know the pros and cons of the management style you chose.</p>

<h1>For early management</h1>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Build management and organizational structures around the strengths your company needs to succeed.</li>
<li>Recognize and plan for the weaknesses that you know are inherent in the structures you pick.</li>
<li>Build great habits around communication and decision-making when everyone still knows each other well.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h1>Culture</h1>

<h2>Why you need it from start</h2>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>In a small team, every one can learn from founders, but when it scales, information gets lost.</li>
<li>“Culture is defined by differing from the norm. It can’t be like everyone else’s.”</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h2>Practical methods of building it</h2>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>The CEO must own encoding and transmitting culture.</li>
<li>Write down what makes your company different.</li>
<li>Describe culture in ways that  make people think and debate rather than universally agree.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h2>Facebook&rsquo;s lesson</h2>

<blockquote><p>Facebook’s “Move Fast and Break Things” tagline is a canonical example. It has challenged every new employee to realize it&rsquo;s worth some amount of risk to keep innovating, experimenting and moving forward. And to avoid becoming overly conservative even when a mistake could impact a billion people.</p></blockquote>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<blockquote><p>Building great management and great culture is never easy nor complete, but both are much harder to tackle when product has already shipped. Take advantage of the benefits of build phase to start early and tackle these hard problems before they become so massive they put the company’s success on the line.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to listen to classic music?]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/03/16/how-to-listen-to-classic-music/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T20:22:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/03/16/how-to-listen-to-classic-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>怎么听“严肃/高雅”音乐，听不懂怎么办，是个很常见的问题。于是就有这样一个中央音乐学院副院长，用毫无门槛的姿态，给中央党校的未来土豪领导们<a href="http://goo.gl/USy6en">解释了这个问题</a>。讲座很有技巧，深入浅出，有很多现场赏析来辅佐解释，当然最重要的还是内容本身：</p>

<blockquote><p>听懂音乐?</p>

<ul>
<li>中国古有“高山流水遇知音”的追求，导致大家以此为最高境界，追求“听懂”音乐</li>
<li>客观上音乐不是视觉，很难实现“听懂”需要的视觉联想</li>
<li>实际上音乐确实能够产生联想，主要靠&#8221;联觉&#8221;现象，声音高低快慢会对应相应的其他物理感受，冷热快慢积极消极等</li>
<li>音乐无所谓听不听的懂，听懂的是什么，因为没有固定答案，放松听就可以</li>
</ul>


<p>为什么听&#8221;严肃/高雅&#8221;音乐?</p>

<ul>
<li>“严肃/高雅”音乐比通俗音乐更复杂

<ul>
<li>随年龄、理解力、注意力增长，人对通俗音乐会觉得太简单</li>
<li>如果确实不喜欢呢？有的复杂的东西需要一定耐受力，还没有体会到复杂背后的美感</li>
<li>“没有强烈的期待，就没有强烈的感动”，复杂音乐像看足球，懂球的人会关注过程，不懂的人只看进球，产生的感受无法和关注了过程的人相比</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>培养感性能力</p>

<ul>
<li>完善的人需要获得幸福条件的能力（理性），也需要体验幸福感受的能力（感性能力）</li>
<li>国人不重视发展感性能力——导致感觉器官不发达，能解释很多现象

<ul>
<li>有物质财富但感觉不到幸福</li>
<li>停留在简单的感官刺激（吃、喝酒、赌、搓脚等）——容易腻</li>
<li>在很多其他方面麻木，音乐、旅游等没兴趣，感受不到艺术的存在</li>
<li>察觉不到审美需求，在做取舍判断时毫不顾忌审美</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>前面的部分讲的是音乐本身，后面引申到艺术的必要性。为什么公众普遍不重视艺术，这是个很好的解释。感性也是一种能力，需要培养和发展。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zen of programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/zen-of-programming/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-28T23:36:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/02/28/zen-of-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When many things become mature, they start to get a simple philosophy, but cover a lot of thoughts underneath. That&rsquo;s the abstraction of all complexities. Like Zen.</p>

<p>This phenomenon can be seen on some hand made craft, like a program from a programmer. But it&rsquo;s always difficult to expose the beauty of it, with an easy, friendly way that non-programmer can recognize. Or say, only real master with deep love of life can do it right. Like <a href="http://www.baroque.me/">this one</a>.</p>

<p>Can&rsquo;t express my praise enough on this.</p>

<ul>
<li>Need sounds on while you watching the balls.</li>
<li>The circles, strings, with right speed, are playing Bach&rsquo;s Cello Suites in a way I&rsquo;ve never thought of.</li>
<li>Just as beautiful as Bach&rsquo;s Cello Suites.</li>
</ul>


<p>From the <a href="http://blog.chenalexander.com/2011/baroque-bach-cello/">author&rsquo;s words</a>, you can know the complexities behind scene. Also some <a href="http://work.chenalexander.com/">other works</a> from <a href="http://work.chenalexander.com/bio">him</a>. If you still remember the <a href="http://www.google.com/logos/2011/lespaul.html">string logo of google</a>, yes, it&rsquo;s created by him.</p>

<p>When a person become mature, he&rsquo;ll also get a simple mind, be generous, friendly to others and himself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nathan Marz's sharing]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/02/24/nathan-marzs-sharing/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T23:02:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/02/24/nathan-marzs-sharing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://nathanmarz.com">Nathan Marz</a> is the author of <a href="https://github.com/nathanmarz/storm">storm</a>. Just read an interview of him from &ldquo;Programmer&rdquo; magazine. Here&rsquo;re the <a href="http://nathanmarz.com/blog/interview-with-programmer-magazine.html">English</a> and <a href="http://www.csdn.net/article/2014-02-05/2818311-Storm-Nathan-Marz">Chinese</a> version. Some quotes here.</p>

<blockquote><p>Q: How to improve your skills as a programmer?</p>

<p>A: I get better by doing a lot of programming and trying new things. One of the best ways to become a better programmer is to learn new programming languages. By learn I mean more than just learning the syntax of the language, I mean understanding the language&rsquo;s idioms and writing something substantial in it. &hellip;</p>

<p><br/></p>

<p>Q: Main lessons you learned in the last few years of your professional career?</p>

<p>A: Feedback is everything. For product development and managing a team.</p>

<p><br/></p>

<p>Q: Process of building a software system?</p>

<p>A: The general idea is to avoid making &ldquo;general&rdquo; or &ldquo;extensible&rdquo; solutions until you have a very deep understanding of the problem domain. &hellip; The sequence is &ldquo;First make it possible. Then make it beautiful. Then make it fast.&rdquo;</p>

<p><br/></p>

<p>Q: What are the best programmers in common do you think?</p>

<p>A: The best programmers are obsessed with improving as programmers. They love exploring new programming languages and new ideas. Another key trait of great programmers is a &ldquo;getting stuff done&rdquo; mentality. It&rsquo;s far more important to get something working than to make the perfect design. Plus a great programmer recognizes that you can&rsquo;t make a perfect design without first having something working that you can learn from.</p>

<p><br/></p>

<p>Q: What do you do in improve your writing skill?</p>

<p>A: Write a lot. Get feedback. Read a lot and try to learn from great writers.</p></blockquote>

<p>Sometimes, experience is important not because it tells something new, but because it confirms something you know.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Non blocking pipe]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/01/22/non-blocking-pipe/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-22T21:54:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2014/01/22/non-blocking-pipe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Met a problem of linux pipe from daily work, finally got me to write a small tool to get rid of it. Worth to note.</p>

<h1>Motivation</h1>

<p>I&rsquo;ve built a central logging system based on logstash. It looks like this, basically,</p>

<br/>


<p><img src="http://typd.github.io/images/posts/2014-01-22/1.png" alt="" /></p>

<br/>


<p>Then every program use logstash as a shipper to redirect its log into the broker, which is a redis as message queue. As this <a href="http://adam.heroku.com/past/2011/4/1/logs_are_streams_not_files/">blog</a> recommended, treatting log as stream rather than files, linux pipe make it possible to guide the stream to anywhere easily.</p>

<pre><code>application | java -jar logstash.jar agent -f logstash.conf
</code></pre>

<p>The problem occurs when the redis was accidently down, causes</p>

<ul>
<li>Logstash blocked, which is a designed behavior of <a href="http://logstash.net/docs/1.3.3/life-of-an-event">logstash</a>. It says &ldquo;dropping messages or unlimited queue lenght are both undesirable behavior&rdquo;, so simply leaves no option and get it blocked.</li>
<li>Then caused upstream application blocked, too! This is done by OS after the pipe buffer is filled up. This is a more serious problem as it&rsquo;s not easy to change OS default behavior.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<h1>Solution?</h1>

<p>Two possible solutions</p>

<ul>
<li>Introduce a log file, start logstash as a independent service to monitor it. This is the opposed way of the above blog recommended. This brings unnecessary disk IO, and you may need other things to avoid the log file getting too big, etc.</li>
<li>Make the pipe non-blocking. But how?</li>
</ul>


<h1>How</h1>

<p>After investigation, logstash doesn&rsquo;t provide non-blocking option, described as above, although it should be easy to do. Why not write one? Here&rsquo;s the result,</p>

<pre><code>application | non_blocking_pipe java -jar logstash.jar agent -f logstash.conf
</code></pre>

<p>&ldquo;non_blocking_pipe&rdquo; is a middleware to read input from upstream, and send to downstream. It uses a fixed size internal queue. If downstream becomes blocked or slower than upstream, just drop the messages and remain reading inputs. A sidenote, why not do &ldquo;application | non_blocking_pipe | downstream&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s because the middle component has to own the downstream as a subprocess, in order to know if it&rsquo;s blocked.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/typd/non-blocking-pipe">Code available here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading notes of More Joel on Software]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/12/20/reading-notes-of-more-joel-on-software/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-20T23:09:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/12/20/reading-notes-of-more-joel-on-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>日复一日写程序，扪心自问，从junior到senior，积累的是什么。<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel Spolsky</a>就是一个略带奇葩乐于分享能满足我好奇心的人，<a href="http://book.douban.com/subject/4163938/">More Joel on Software</a>记录了他博客上关于软件开发的随笔。一些启发性的内容：</p>

<blockquote><p>我的第一次BillG审查</p>

<ul>
<li>BillG真的会以技术视角审视决定，做批判性思考。软件公司要让懂编程的人来管理</li>
</ul>


<p>寻找优秀的程序员</p>

<ul>
<li>优秀的程序员大多不在人才市场。他们优秀以至于大多数时候不需要找工作，只要在自己喜欢的地方待着就可以</li>
</ul>


<p>寻找优秀的程序员之实战指南</p>

<ul>
<li>假定你要找的是优秀程序员</li>
<li>站在求职者的位置设身处地的想，对方会抓住任何细节来形成对你公司的印象，所以要十分注重对方参观办公室的体验，如果有必要，把怪人藏起来</li>
<li>让一流新员工挑选他们想参与的项目，使用非必要的热门新技术（让他们开心一些），认同公司，给他们的工作带来意义</li>
</ul>


<p>三种管理方法————军事化管理</p>

<ul>
<li>军队需要个体牺牲以达到整体最优结果，因此要养成个人服从命令的天性；软件公司中因为程序员可以轻易离开，不能用这种方法</li>
</ul>


<p>三种管理方法————经济利益驱动法</p>

<ul>
<li>假定每个人的行为动机都是金钱，给予物质奖励或惩罚，创造动机；比如用bug数或各种考核指标和奖励惩罚挂钩</li>
<li>问题：让内部激励（自发的，强有力的）变成了外部激励（被动的，弱的）</li>
<li>更大问题，人有追求局部利益最大化的倾向，而程序员又是高智商群体，会想各种办法让报酬最大化，鼓励程序员和制度博弈</li>
<li>其实这根本不是管理，更像是管理的退位，或者说是一种设计精巧的推卸责任的方法，不愿承担责任找到把事情做得更好的方法。它是一个信号，表明管理层根本不知道如何引导人们做出更好的工作，所以强迫每个人在制度框架下自己想办法把事情做好。当你创造一种制度的时候，不能放弃自己的职责，不能通过发钱的方式来训练他们。</li>
</ul>


<p>三种管理方法————认同法</p>

<ul>
<li>使人们认同你的目标。比如聘请实习生到纽约的一个目的是让他们喜欢纽约继而留在本公司。</li>
<li>提供必要的信息让员工可以自己做决策。</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>给计算机系学生的建议</p>

<ul>
<li>条目很多，这是比较特别的两点：

<ul>
<li>毕业前练好写作：最有权威和影响力的程序员往往是表达能力强的程序员，能清晰、自如、有说服力的传达观点。即使如Linus，如果不是超强的表达能力，Linux也无法取得如此成功。</li>
<li>学好微观经济学：一个理解基本商业规则的程序员会更有价值。我看到过太多提出疯狂想法的程序员，也许在代码上可行，但在资本世界中毫无意义。</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>火星人的耳机 和 为什么Microsoft Office的文件格式如此复杂</p>

<ul>
<li>这两篇的内容有相似之处，讲解为什么IE、Office套件会成为事实标准而又积重难返。文章写得深入浅出，以至于我觉得很难概括描述，还是推荐读原文理解。大致的感受如下</li>
<li>一些背景和假设

<ul>
<li>软件开发中分为两派，理论派和务实派。理论派类似于现实中的左派，希望激进的推行标准前进，以及完备的测试；务实派更愿意妥协，兼容性更重要</li>
<li>开发中测试永远无法达到完全自动和完备的程度，因为如果可以达到，那测试代码的信息熵和软件代码的信息熵将等量。</li>
<li>对很多技术标准来说，最初的版本难免有历史局限性，外界的实现难免会出现多个有细微差别的版本；标准更新时，就会受限于兼容性</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>在浏览器, Windows和Office的问题上类似，解析器A被认为能够解析满足标准B的实现C，微软承担了制定最初版本A1和B1的角色，虽然不完美，但因此产生了大量兼容它们的C1, C2 .. Cn。为了升级，微软推出了向前兼容的新版本A2, B2，继而出现了更多的实现C21, C22, .. C2n。如此B的束缚作用逐渐淡化，最终变成了A1, .. An 对 C11, &hellip; Cnx的多对多兼容。所以每次升级都要在理论和务实间妥协，至少你根本没法放弃现有用户，而完全追求&#8221;更好的标准&#8221;，这意味着用户会放弃你的标准。</li>
<li>Joel没有给出怎么做才会更好。我觉得这些问题确实很难避免，造成的原因有

<ul>
<li>问题足够复杂，网页、OS、Office格式</li>
<li>野蛮式的快速发展，对商业利益的追求，最初的日子里，对标准的优化并不是最重要，添加feature，满足需求，兼容老用户才是</li>
<li>事实上对实现和标准制定的垄断加重了问题</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>飙高音</p>

<ul>
<li>程序员的生产效率差别巨大，即使在“优秀”的程序员间，生产效率差别依然巨大</li>
<li>平庸程序员很难成为优秀程序员</li>
<li>软件行业赢家通吃</li>
</ul>


<p>揉一揉，搓一搓</p>

<ul>
<li>大多数情况下，重构代码比重写代码更划算</li>
<li>老代码并不像看上去那么一无是处，其实包含了大量以往的劳动成果、错误修正和经验，重构比重写节约大量劳动</li>
</ul>


<p>五个为什么</p>

<ul>
<li>SLA的最大问题，缺乏制定标准必须的统计资料，无法知道多长的运行时间才是正常的。</li>
<li>日本丰田创始人的思想：当某个地方出错的时候，就问为什么，一遍遍的追问，直到找到根本原因为止

<ul>
<li>机房连接中断了，为什么？网线接口好像不工作了</li>
<li>为什么？网速/双工模式不匹配造成</li>
<li>为什么？交换机的网速开关设在了自动调节，而没有被手动设置在固定档</li>
<li>为什么？许多年前，我们就直到有可能发生此故障，但始终没有写出一份书面技术文档，用于知道交换机在生产环境中配置</li>
<li>为什么？我们总是很狭隘的看待技术文档，觉得只有在找不到管理员的情况下才需要看。没有意识到要把它作为技术操作的标准和确认清单</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>为服务稳定性设定一个静态值为目标意义不大，而是需要一个不断改进工作质量的流程。如搭建一个fail log，记录每次中断以及完整的时候分析，找到根本原因。</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>可以看出Joel对于程序员极为重视，以至于让我觉得有些过度了，而较少谈到程序员的弱点和限制，虽然这样会让程序员更爱读这些文章。就我的感受，程序员确实是十分聪明的群体，热爱专注于解决问题，但局限性同样明显，专注的问题之外的领域往往被他们忽略。Joel以上的一些观点其实并不多高深，尤其关于管理方法，也许对于管理专业而言是基本常识，但在草莽的软件行业，正是普遍被忽略的。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The fight will]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/30/the-fight-will/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T22:13:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/30/the-fight-will</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just watched <a href="http://www.letv.com/ptv/vplay/2181407.html">this documentary</a> of Jeremy Lin, highlights the crazy days of him last year. The story looks like all other inspiration ones,</p>

<ul>
<li>He has played well all before graduating from Harvard, until has to think about the future.</li>
<li>Luckily Golden States team gave an offer. But mostly because he played with the son of the team&rsquo;s new owner. Been cut finally.</li>
<li>Been picked again. Travel between lower level league and main league back and force several times. Been cut again.</li>
<li>Got another offer from struggling NY. Screw up a game. Slept on a short couch before the possible last game in career, at the edge of being cut the 3rd time.</li>
<li>For someone stands right besides the dream, but others give you no hope, would think he has nothing to lose. If this is the last game, you&rsquo;ll be very concentrated and do all you can. After scored, he thought &ldquo;they have no reason to cut me now&rdquo;. That emotion pushed him to a new level.</li>
<li>Then everyone knows him. Before the game with Kobe, Kobe was asked about him and answered in a fuzzy or ambiguous way, &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know who he is, who you&rsquo;re talking about&rdquo;. Anyone wants to survive on the league should not accept that. After the game, he was asked &ldquo;do you think Kobe knows you now?&rdquo;. He was tempted to say &ldquo;who the hell is Kobe?&rdquo;, but then he thought &ldquo;what would Jesus do?&rdquo;, answered &ldquo;you need to ask Kobe&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>Lin got to a new level after the journey. &ldquo;You don&rsquo;t get better if you win all the time. You get better when you lose. You look like yourself more. Go through tough time, that&rsquo;s a perfect plan&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve watched several other NBA players&#8217; documentaries before, too. All of these can bring you strong emotion with exciting shots, slum dunks, especially when you relate them to the stories behind scene. The competition sports then look like a reality show more. Money, ethnic, culture, nationality are involved to the game. Just as complex as life. But after you have accepted that, it&rsquo;s still simple: your strength helps you to get on the stage, your faith determines where you gonna stop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experience sharing from a senior dev lead]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/26/experience-sharing-from-a-senior-dev-lead/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T22:41:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/26/experience-sharing-from-a-senior-dev-lead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A senior dev lead of my company did a experience sharing to our office. Below are the highlights.</p>

<h1>Incidents</h1>

<p>He titled himslef the &ldquo;incident reporter&rdquo;, as he thinks this is an important role. Something he did for incidents</p>

<ul>
<li>Monitor and be pro-active</li>
<li>Log events as the incident evolves</li>
<li>Post-mortem analysis and followup

<ul>
<li>Build better alerting, monitoring and tracking</li>
<li>Look for other failure signs</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Fail blog</li>
</ul>


<p>And he also mentioned after incident&rsquo;ve happened, it&rsquo;s a good chance for you to go over the related log and find defects you didn&rsquo;t pay enough notice before.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>The service checklist, when building a new service</h1>

<ul>
<li>Isolated, decomposed: do one thing, and do it right</li>
<li>Documentation

<ul>
<li>API</li>
<li>Discoverable</li>
<li>Node list, deployment procedures</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Devable

<ul>
<li>Bootstrap procedure: as easy as possible</li>
<li>Dev env should be as closely to prod as possible</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Staging environment</li>
<li>Load balancing / redundancy / self healing</li>
<li>Fault tolerant: anything can fail

<ul>
<li>Infrastructure failures

<ul>
<li>disk, ram, network switches</li>
<li>DNS stability</li>
<li>data center failure (rack, power, network, disaster)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Software stack pattern failure

<ul>
<li>date bomb (leap year, leap second, cert expiration)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Dependency slowness</li>
<li>Auto start</li>
<li>Automated deployment</li>
<li>Automated tests</li>
<li>Log management

<ul>
<li>logrotate</li>
<li>centeralized logging</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Self monitoring

<ul>
<li>heartbeat</li>
<li>machine monitoring</li>
<li>exception alerts (rate limit emails)</li>
<li>metrics (metricsd, graphite)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h1>Others</h1>

<p>In early days, some star devs tend to be heroism. But that doesn&rsquo;t work well as company becomes mature. Some better practices as we&rsquo;ve grown up</p>

<ul>
<li>Better documentation</li>
<li>More communication

<ul>
<li>know what does each team focus</li>
<li>prioritize the projects based on all teams&#8217; needs</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Rotate dev among teams, balance the output and the underlying benefits</li>
</ul>


<h1>And more thoughts on him</h1>

<ul>
<li>Good attitude on work</li>
<li>Logical thinking, right judgement, and good perception on tech.</li>
<li>Absolutely smart. I have to say that&rsquo;s a gift not everyone has, or trainable.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My toolbelt]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/23/my-toolbelt/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-23T13:16:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/23/my-toolbelt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being a developer facing a screen almost all the awake time, sooner or later you&rsquo;ll know an up to date toolbelt will make your life easier.</p>

<p><a href="http://typd.github.io/pages/toolbelt/">Here are the tools</a> I use for my daily life and work. Things are upgrading fast so that I&rsquo;ll update the list continuously.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Laptop</h1>

<ul>
<li>mac: developer friendly, worth the price.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred</a>: shortcut to what you want</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/fikovnik/ShiftIt">Shiftit</a>: manage window size and position for OSX</li>
<li><a href="https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/">Chrome</a>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/autopager-chrome/mmgagnmbebdebebbcleklifnobamjonh?hl=zh-CN">Auto pager</a></li>
<li><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/evernote-web-clipper/pioclpoplcdbaefihamjohnefbikjilc?hl=zh-CN">Evernote button</a></li>
<li><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/vimium/dbepggeogbaibhgnhhndojpepiihcmeb">Vimium</a>: This is AWESOME! Use keyboard to open links rather than mouse.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://dropbox.com">dropbox</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mac-downloader.com/">Folx</a>: download manager for mac</li>
<li><a href="http://coppertino.com/vox/">Vox</a>: the best music player on mac as I know.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.zsh.org/">zsh</a>: a better shell with many improvements than bash</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">oh-my-zsh</a>: provides nice themes for zsh, highly configurable</li>
<li><a href="http://www.vim.org/">vim</a>: I&rsquo;m a vim user and still learning it. Haven&rsquo;t tried emacs yet.

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/scrooloose/nerdtree">nerdtree</a>: a tree explorer plugin.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ</a>: a easy to use, highly configurable IDE for java. I prefer it to eclipse.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/">PyCharm</a>: IDE for python. A free version is available.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/typd/cmd-dict">Command line En&lt;&ndash;>Zh dict</a>: own work</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/typd/cmd-search">Command line search tool</a>: own work, search text within files</li>
</ul>


<h1>Tool sites</h1>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.evernote.com">Evernote</a>: besides taking notes, I also use it as a bookmark system like del.icio.us</li>
<li><a href="http://www.feedly.com">Feedly</a>: R.I.P. google reader</li>
<li><a href="http://www.github.com">Github</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.douban.com">Douban</a>: I use it as a database for my read books and watched movies</li>
</ul>


<h1>Good stuff online</h1>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://rubyrogues.com/">Podcast &ndash; Ruby Rogus</a>: each week 4-6 rubiers pick a topic and share their thoughts</li>
<li><a href="https://learn.thoughtbot.com/giantrobots">Podcast &ndash; Thoughbot Giant Robots</a>: weekly technical interview</li>
</ul>


<h1>Developing and engineering</h1>

<h2>General</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://python.org/">Python</a>: &ldquo;Explicit is better than implicit&rdquo;; prefer python3 to python2, as it has many improvements</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a>: &ldquo;Convention over configuration&rdquo;</li>
<li><a href="http://pryrepl.org/">Pry</a>: a drop-in replacement to irb, many amazing features</li>
<li><a href="http://git-scm.com">Git</a>: no more svn</li>
</ul>


<h2>Project monitoring</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://logstash.net/">Logstash</a>: highly configurable tool to manage events and program logs</li>
<li><a href="http://graphite.wikidot.com/">Graphite</a>: collect metrics from services and do scalable realtime graphing</li>
</ul>


<h2>Continuous integration</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://jenkins-ci.org/">Jenkins</a>: still the best CI tool, easy to use, configurable, powerful</li>
</ul>


<h2>Machine Management</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/saltstack/salt">Salt</a>: use config files to manage machines</li>
<li><a href="http://docs.fabfile.org/en/1.8/">Fabric</a>: execute commands remotely over ssh</li>
<li><a href="http://mmonit.com/monit/">Monit</a>: deployed to target machine for managing and monitor machine status</li>
<li><a href="http://upstart.ubuntu.com/">Upstart</a>: a better system service management tool than System-V</li>
</ul>


<h2>Misc</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.highcharts.com/">Highcharts</a>: a js library to render nice charts</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Movie story line visualization]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/12/movie-story-line-visualization/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T22:32:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/12/movie-story-line-visualization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was just watching a conf video which mentioned a graph I&rsquo;ve seen before.</p>

<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/movie_narrative_charts.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve interviewed a candidate from a research department of that company. He showed me this graph and said his project was about automatically generating store line graph like this. Use algorithms like DP, to re-order and group the character lines, reduce cross point count, etc. Those ideas make sense to me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The right way of logging]]></title>
    <link href="http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/06/the-right-way-of-logging/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-06T22:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://typd.github.io/blog/2013/11/06/the-right-way-of-logging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After read the 12-factor app spec, I took a close look to the logging section. For an application, it feels so nature to write logs to a file. But I just feel something isn&rsquo;t right.</p>

<ul>
<li>Do I need a cleaner tool like log rotate, or just pretend they&rsquo;re small forever?</li>
<li>To debug something, I&rsquo;m just forced to ssh across ocean and use a crappy vim on the host to find something weird.</li>
</ul>


<p>&ldquo;Elephant in the room&rdquo;. Until I read <a href="http://adam.heroku.com/past/2011/4/1/logs_are_streams_not_files/">this post</a> in the spec, things become clear. Now here&rsquo;s my understanding.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The application log looks like a stream, and then it should be a stream. We normally append it to a file, just because that&rsquo;s the most obvious way of treating it. But it&rsquo;s defenitly not the only way. In fact for logging, the application&rsquo;s duty is done once it outputs to the stream. The logic of handling (append, rotate, clean) files, should (or say &ldquo;can&rdquo;) not be a part of the application.</p>

<p>But what to do then if the application doesn&rsquo;t handle the log stream output. It&rsquo;s actually easier and more robust to take it out. Tools like Unix pipe, and <a href="http://logstash.net/">logstash</a> or <a href="https://github.com/fluent/fluentd">fluend</a> are more good at it than any application side logging lib.</p>

<p>For simple file logging, you can use</p>

<pre><code>$ mydaemon &gt;&gt; /var/log/mydaemon.log
</code></pre>

<p>For distributed logging,</p>

<pre><code>$ mydaemon | logger
</code></pre>

<p>Or still want a log file</p>

<pre><code>$ mydaemon | tee /var/log/mydaemon.log | logger
</code></pre>

<p>The &ldquo;logger&rdquo; is a placeholder for tools like logstash, which can be assembled into any kind of pipe line easily. Logstash has <a href="http://logstash.net/docs/1.2.2/">doc</a> and <a href="http://cookbook.logstash.net/">cookbooks</a>. Just choose the input, output, filter as you need.</p>

<p>A typical setup may be:</p>

<pre><code>log stream
=&gt; shipper: send log through udp out of the host
=&gt; message queue: redis, mongodb, etc.
=&gt; parser: parse each line to get timestamp, attributes, etc. May ingest parse logic here
=&gt; elastic search: build index according to the parse result
=&gt; web ui: for centralized viewing, querying, alerting, etc.
</code></pre>

<p>Move the elephant out of the room.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
